<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<refentry id="tgtd.8">

<refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>tgtd</refentrytitle>
	<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
</refmeta>


<refnamediv>
	<refname>tgtd</refname>
	<refpurpose>The SCSI Target Daemon</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
		<command>tgtd</command>
	</cmdsynopsis>
	
	<cmdsynopsis>
		<command>tgtd</command>
		<arg choice="opt">-C --control-port &lt;INTEGER&gt;</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-d --debug &lt;INTEGER&gt;</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-f --foregound</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">-h --help</arg>
		<arg choice="opt">--iscsi &lt;...&gt;</arg>
	</cmdsynopsis>
	
</refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para>
      Tgtd is a SCSI Target daemon. It can be used to provide SCSI target
      service to a network. The most common service is iSCSI but other services are also
      supported.
    </para>
  </refsect1>


  <refsect1><title>Device types</title>
    <para>
      Tgtd provides support for both emulated and passthrough of real devices.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <screen format="linespecific">
    Tgtd can emulate the following types of devices:
    
    disk       : Normal disk device. Emulates a SCSI harddisk.
    tape       : Tape device. Emulates a SCSI tape drive.
    cd         : CD device. Emulates a SCSI DVD burner.
    changer    : Media changer. Emulate the changer device for a virtual tape library or DVD jukebox.
  </screen>

  <refsect1>
    <title>OPTIONS</title>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>-d --debug &lt;INTEGER&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Set to non-zero value to activate additional debugging messages to
	    be logged.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry><term>-f --foreground</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Run the daemon in the foreground.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry><term>-h --help</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Print help text to the screen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry><term>-C --control-port &lt;INTEGER&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    This comamnd is used to specify the control port to use for
	    this instance of tgtd. This allows to run multiple instances of
	    TGTD on a host.
          </para>
          <para>
	    TGTADM has a matching argument to control which instance to connect
	    to.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry><term>--iscsi &lt;...&gt;</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    ISCSI specific options.
            See the ISCSI section below for options specific to this frontend.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>


  <refsect1><title>ISCSI options</title>
    <para>
      These parameters apply only to the iSCSI frontend.
    </para>

    <refsect2><title>portal=&lt;ip-address[:port]&gt;</title>
      <para>
	This option is used to bind tgtd to a specific ip-address/portal and/or
	port. By default tgtd will bind to port 3260 on the wildcard address.
	The ip-address part (before the ":") can be missing to designate the
	wildcard address with a none-default port.
      </para>
      <para>
      Example: to bind tgtd to a specific address and port
      <screen format="linespecific">
	tgtd --iscsi portal=192.0.2.1:3260
      </screen>
      Example: to bind tgtd to any address but a none-default port
      <screen format="linespecific">
	tgtd --iscsi portal=:3251
      </screen>
      </para>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2><title>nop_interval=&lt;integer&gt;</title>
      <para>
	This sets the default interval for sending NOP-OUT to probe for
	connected initiators.
	This parameter only controls the default value for targets.
	Individual targets can be controlled using tgtadm.
      </para>
      <para>
	The default value is 0 which means that the feature is disabled
	TGTD will not send any NOP-OUT probes.
      </para>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2><title>nop_count=&lt;integer&gt;</title>
      <para>
	This sets the default value for after how many failed probes TGTD
	will consider the initiator dead and tear down the session.
	This parameter only controls the default value for targets.
	Individual targets can be controlled using tgtadm.
      </para>
      <para>
	The default value is 0.
      </para>
      <para>
      Example: send NOP-OUT every 5 seconds and abort the session after
      6 failures.
      <screen format="linespecific">
	tgtd --iscsi portal=192.0.2.1:3260,nop_interval=5,nop_count=6
      </screen>
      </para>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>


  <refsect1><title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <para>
      tgtadm(8), tgt-admin(8), tgtimg(8), tgt-setup-lun(8).
      <ulink url="http://stgt.sourceforge.net/"/>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1><title>COPYRIGHT/LICENSE</title>
<literallayout>
This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at
your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses/.
</literallayout>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
